are we
[Music]
ready
the Ping to start in a minute he's going
to raise his hand and signal that I'm on
just a minute though let him
sett
[Music]
okay okay give me the signal then when
you want me to start
[Music]
okay this is linear algebra lecture four
and uh the first thing I have to do is
something that was on the list for last
time but here it is now what's the
inverse of a product If I multiply two
matrices together and I know they're
inverses how do I get the inverse of a *
B so I know what inverses means for a
single Matrix a and for a matrix B what
Matrix do I multiply by to get the
identity if I have a okay that that'll
be simple but so basic
then uh then I'm going to use that to I
will have a product of
matrices and the product that we'll meet
will be these elimination matrices and
the net result of today's
lecture is the big formula for
elimination so that the net result of
today's lecture is this is this great
way to look
at Galan elimination we know that we get
from a to U by elimination we know the
set but now we get the right way to look
at it AAL Lu so that's the high point
for today okay can I take the easy part
the the first step first uh
so suppose a is
invertible and of course it's going to
be a big question when is a matrix
invertible but let's say a is invertible
and B is invertible then what Matrix
gives me the inverse of ab so so that's
the direct question what's the inverse
of ab do I multiply those separate
inverses yes I I multiply the two
matrices a inverse and B inverse but
what order do I
multiply in reverse order and you see
why so that the right thing to put here
is B inverse a inverse that's the
inverse I'm ask I we we can just check
that AB times that Matrix gives the
identity
okay so why once again it's this fact
that I can move parentheses around I can
actually I can just erase them all and
do the multiplications any way I want to
so what's the right multiplication to do
first B * B inverse this this product
here is the
identity then a * the identity is the
identity and then finally a * a inverse
gives the identity
so forg a dumb dumb example in the book
it's just why you why do you uh do this
inverse things in reverse order it's
just like taking you take off your shoes
you take off your socks then the good
way to invert that process is socks back
on first
then sorry okay I'm sorry that's on the
pap but all
[Music]
that that will bring a transpose into
the picture so if I transpose the
identity
Matrix what do I have the identity right
if I if I exchange rows and columns the
identity is a symmetric Matrix it
doesn't know the difference if I
transpose these
guys that product then again it turns
out that I have to trans I to reverse
the order
I can transpose them separately but when
I multiply those transposes come in the
opposite order so it's a inverse
transpose time a
transpose giving the identity so that's
this equation it just comes directly
from that one but this equation tells me
what I wanted to know namely what is the
inverse of this guy a
transpose what's the inverse of that if
I transpose
Matrix what what's the inverse of the
result and this equation tells me that
here it is this
is this
is the inverse this is the inverse of
a inverse of
a of
a I
just a put a big circle around that
because that's the
answer we that's the best answer we
could hope
for that if you want to know the inverse
of a
[Music]
transpose and you know the inverse of a
then you just transpose that so in in to
put it another way transposing and
inversing you can do it either order for
a single
me okay so that these are like basic
facts
that we can now use oh so now I put it
to
use I put it to use by thinking we're
we're really
completing uh the subject of
elimination
actually
I the thing about elimination
is it it's the right way to to
understand what the Matrix has got this
AAL Lu is the most basic factorization
of a
matrix um it's it's I always worry that
you will think this course is
just uh is all
elimination it's just row
operations and please don't it it will
will be beyond
that uh but it's the right uh it's the
right uh
algebra to do first okay so I'm coming
near the end of it but I want to get it
in a decent form so my decent form is
Matrix
form I have a matrix
a let's suppose it's a good Matrix I can
do elimination no row exchanges so no
row exchanges for
now
pivots all fine nothing zero in the
pivot position I get you the very end
which is U so I get from a to U and I
want to know what's the connection how
is a related to you and this is going to
tell me that there's a matrix L that's
connect okay can I can I do it for a 2X
two
first okay 2X two uh elimination okay so
I'll do it under
here okay so let let my Matrix a
b uh let's let's just we'll keep it
simple say two and an eight so we know
that the first pivot is a two and the
multiplier is going to be a four and
then let me put a one here and what
number do I not want to put
there four I don't want a four there
because in that case the second pivot
would not we wouldn't have a second
pivot the Matrix would be singular
General screw up okay so let me put some
other number here like
seven
okay okay now I want to operate on that
with my elementary
Matrix so what what's the elementary
Matrix I'm I'll strictly speaking it's
E21 because it's it's the guy that's
going to produce a zero in that position
and it's going to produce you in one
in one shot because it's just a 2X two
Matrix uh so
21 and I'm going to take four of those
away from those produce that zero and
leave a three there and that's you and
what's the Matrix that did it quick
review then what's the elimination
Elementary Matrix
E21 it's one thanks
and -41 right good okay so that's I I
you see the difference between this and
what I'm shooting for I'm shooting for a
on one side
and the other matrices is on the other
side of the equation okay so I can do
that right
away now now here's going to be my a l
and you won't have any trouble telling
me what uh so a is still
L is what you're going to tell me and U
is still 2 1
03 okay so what's l in this
case well first so how is L related to
this e
guys it's the inverse because I want to
multiply through by the inverse of this
which will put the identity here and the
inverse will show up there and I'll call
it l
so what is the inverse of this remember
that's uh those those elimination
matrices are easy to
invert the inverse Matrix for this one
is 1
Z
four it it has the plus sign because it
adds back what this removed okay do you
want so if if we did the numbers right
we must
this this should be correct okay and of
course it is that that says the first
row is Right four * the first row plus
the second row is 87 good okay that's
simple 2 by two but it already shows the
form that we're headed
for it shows so what's the L stand for
why the letter L if youu stood for upper
triangular then of course L stands stand
for lower triangle and actually it has
ones on the
diagonal where this thing has a pivots
on the diet oh sometimes uh we may want
to separate out the pivot so can I just
mention that sometimes we could also
write this as we could have this
one41 I'll just show you how I would
divide out this Matrix of here 2 3
there's a diagonal
matrix and I just whatever is left is
here now what's
left if I divide this first row by two
to pull out the two then I have a one
and
A2 and if I divide the second row by
three to pull out the three then I have
a one so that's the if this is l u this
is
called LZ for pivot U and now it's a
little more
balanced because we have ones on the
diagonal here and here and the diagonal
matrix in the middle so both of those
that lab would would uh produce uh
either
one I I'll basically stay with
L
okay now I have to think of about bigger
than
2x2 right now this was just like easy
exercise and to tell the truth
that this one with a minus sign and this
one with the plus sign uh I mean that's
the only
difference
but with 3x3 there's a more significant
difference let me let me show you how
that works let me let me uh
move up to a
3X3 let's say some Matrix
a
okay let's imagine it's 3x3 I won't
write numbers down for now so what
what's the first elimination step that I
do the first Matrix I multiply it by
what what what letter will I use for
that it's the it going be e to what cuz
it's the it's the first setep will be to
get a to get a zero in that 21 position
and then the next step will be to get a
zero in the 31 position and the final
step will be to get a zero in the 32
position that's what elimination is and
It produced you and again no Ro
CH we
will I'm I'm taking the nice case now
the typical case too when I don't have
to do any roow exchange all I do is
these elimination that okay now suppose
I want that stuff over on the right hand
side as I really do that that's like my
point here I I can multiply these
together to get a matrix e but I want it
over on the right I want its inverse
over
there so what what's the what's the
right
expression now how if I write a and u
what goes
there okay so I've got the inverse of
this I've got three matrices in a row
now and it's there inverses that are
going to show up because each one is
easy to
invert question is what about the whole
bunch how how how easy is it to invert
the whole bunch
so
that's what we know how to do we know
how to invert we should take the
separate inverses but they go in the
opposite order so what goes
here e32 inverse right CU I multiply
from the left by e32 inverse I'll pop it
up next to
you and then we'll come
E31 and then this will be I'll be this
will be the only guy left standing and
that's gone when I do an E21 inverse so
there is L that's that's L
you L is this product of
inverses now you still can ask why is
this guy preferring
inverse and let me explain why let me
explain why why is this product nicer
than this
one this this product turns out to be
better than this
one let me take a typical case
here uh let me let me take a typical
case so so let me I have to do 3x3 for
you to see the see the Improvement 2x
two it was just one e no no problem but
let me go up to this case suppose my
matrices
E21 suppose E21 has has a has aus2 in
there suppose that and now suppose oh
I'll even suppose
E31 is the
identity so I'll just I'm just going to
I'm going to make the point with just a
couple of these okay now this guy will
have do something now let's suppose
minus
five one okay there's
thing
that's a typical case in which we didn't
need an E31 maybe we already had a zero
in that 31
position
okay let me see if that is that going to
be enough to uh show my point let's let
me do that
multiplication okay so if I do that
multiplication this it's like good
practice to multiply these matrices tell
me what's about the diagonal when I do
this
multiplication all zeros when I do this
multiplication I'm going to get one on
the diagonal and Zer
above because what does that say that
says that I'm subtracting rows from
lower rows so nothing nothing is moving
upwards as it did last time in in gal
Jordan okay now so really the uh what I
have to do is check this my - 2 1 0 now
this is so what am I what's that number
that this is the number that I'm really
have in mind that number
is
10 and this one
is what goes here Row three against
column 2 looks like the
minus5
what it's that 10 how did that 10 get in
there I don't like that 10 I mean of
course I don't want to eras it because
it's right but I don't wanted this uh
it's because the 10 got in there because
I subtracted two of Row one from row two
and then I subtracted five of that new
row two from Row three so doing it in
that
order how did Row one affect Row
three well it did CU two of it got
removed from row two and then five of
those got removed from Row three so all
together
10 of Row one got got thrown into Row
three now my point is in the reverse
Direction so now I can do now I'll do
below it I'll do the
inverse okay and of course opposite
order reverse order reverse
order
okay so now this is going to this is the
this is the
E that go goes on the left side left of
a now I'm going to do the inverses in
the opposite order so what's the so so
the opposite order means I put this
Inverse
First and what is this inverse what's
the inverse of
E21 same thing with a plus sign right
for for this for the individual ual
matrices instead of taking away two I
add back two of Row one to row two so no
problem and now in reverse order I want
to invert that just just right I'm doing
just this this so now the inverse is
again the same thing but add in the
five
and now I'll do that
multiplication and I'll get a
happy
result I
hope did I do it right so far yes okay
let me do the multiplication I believe
this comes out so Row one of the answer
is one Z 0 oh I know that all this is
going to be right then I have 2 1 0 so I
get 2 1 0 there
right and what's the third
row what's the third row in this
product just read it out to me the third
row 0
51 because I mean one way to say is this
is saying take one of the last row and
there it is and this is my Matrix L and
it's the one that goes to the left
it goes on the left of you it goes into
this is but what do I mean
here maybe maybe rather than saying left
of a left of U let me write down again
what I mean e a is
U whereas a is l u
okay let me let me make the point now in
words
the the order that the matrices come for
L is the right order the two and the
five
don't sort of
interfere to produce this T in the in
the right order the multipliers just fit
in The Matrix
L that's that's the point that the so
that that if I want to know
l i i no work to do I just keep a record
of what those multipliers were and that
gives me l so so I'll draw the draw the
um so let me let me say so this is this
is the AAL
l so if no row
exchanges
the
multipliers those numbers that we
multiplied rows by and subtracted when
we did an elimination step the
multipliers go
directly into
L
okay so
so so L is this is the way
uh to look at
elimination that uh the you go through
the elimination steps and actually if if
you do it right you can you can throw
away a as you create L
andu it if you think about it those
steps of
elimination as you when you've done when
you've finished with row two of a you've
created a new row two of U which you
have to save and you've created the
multipliers that you used which you have
to save and then you can forget hey so
the because it's all there in L and U so
that's uh that's
like this may this moment is maybe
the the new
uh Insight in elimination that comes
from matri doing it in Matrix form so it
was the product of of
ease is we we can't see what that
product of ease is that the Matrix e is
not particularly attractive what's great
is when we put them on the other side
they're inverses in the opposite order
there the L comes out just far
okay
now oh go so today is a sort of like
practical day
uh can I can we think
together how expensive is
elimination how much how many operations
do we do so so this is another kind of
new topic because I didn't list as on
the program but here it came here it
comes
how
many
operations on an N byn
Matrix
a I mean it's a very practical question
can we can we solve systems of order a
thousand uh in a second second or a
minute or a
week can we solve systems of order a
million in a
second or an hour or a week I mean
what's the if it's n
byn we we often want to takee and bigger
I mean we put in more
information we make this the whole thing
is more accurate for the bigger
matx but it's more expensive too and the
question is how much more expensive if I
go if I have Maes of order 100 let's say
100 by 100 let me let me take n to be
100 say Nal
100 how
many steps are we doing how many
operations are we actually doing that we
not we the and let's Suppose there
aren't any zeros cuz of course if a if a
matrix has got a lot of zeros in good
places we don't have to do those
operations and uh it'll be much
faster but so just think for a moment
about the first step so here's our
Matrix a 100 by
100 and the first step will
be that column is got zeros down here
so it's it's down to 99 by
99 right that that that's really like
the
first uh uh stage of elimination to get
from this 100 by 100 nonzero Matrix to
this stage where the first pivot is
sitting up here and the first row is
okay and the First Column is
okay so essentially I what how many step
did that take you see I'm trying to get
an idea is the
answer proportional to end is the is the
total number of steps in elimination the
total number is a proportion of the n in
which case if I double n from 100 to 200
does it take me twice as long does it
Square so it would take me four times as
long does it Cub so it would take me
eight times as long or is it n factorial
so it would take me 100 times at
home I I think you know from a practical
point of view we have to have some idea
the cost
here so so the these are the questions
let me ask those questions again is it
proportional does it go like n like n s
like n cubed like some higher power of n
like n
factorial where where every step up
multiplies by 100 and then by 101 and
then by 102 which is
it okay so that's the only way I know to
answer that is the it a think through
what we actually had to
do okay so how what was the cost
here well let's see what do I mean by an
operation I guess I
mean
um well an addition yeah no big deal I
guess I mean an addition or a
subtraction or a multiplication or a
division
okay uh and actually what operation am I
doing all the time I'm I'm uh when I
when I multiply Row one by a multiplier
L and I subtract from row
six what's happening there individually
what what's the what's going on If I
multiply I do a multiplication by L and
then a subtraction so I I guess
operation can I count that for the
moment as like one operation or you may
want to count them separately the
typical operation is
multiply plus a
subtract so if I C those
together uh my answer is going to come
out half as many as if if I count them
separately I have a certain number of
multiplies certain number of subtracts
that that's really what I want to do
okay how many have I got to so uh I
think let's
see it's
about well how many re how many
operations to to get from here to here
well maybe one way to look at it is all
these num had to get
changed all the first row didn't get
changed but but all the other rows got
changed at this step so this step well I
guess maybe shall I say it's cost about
this cost about about 100
squar I mean if I changed the first go
then then it would have been exactly 100
squar because that's how many numbers
are here 100 100 squar numberers is the
is the total count of the increase and
oh but this insignificant first row got
changed so I would say about 100
squar okay now what about the next
step so now the first row is fine the
second row is
fine and I'm changing um these zeros
they all fine so what's what's up at the
second step and then you're with me
roughly what's the cost if this if this
first step cost 100 squar about
operations then this one which is really
working on this guy to produce this
costs
about
what how many operations to fix about 99
squares
or 99 * 98 but less right less CU our
problem is getting smaller about 99
squ and then I go down and down the next
one will be 98 squ the next 97 squar and
finally I'm down around 1 squar or where
just
like just Little Numbers the big numbers
are here so the the number of operations
is
about m² plus that was n right n was 100
N2 for the first step then n -1 s then N
- 2 2 finally down to 3 2 and 2 2 and
even 1
2 no way I should have written
that squeeze that in let me try so the
count is n 2 + n -1 2 plus all the way
down to 1
2 that's that's a pretty decent
count yeah admittedly we didn't we
didn't catch every single timey
operation but we got the right
uh the the right leading term here and
what do those add up
to okay so now we're at we're coming to
the punch of this uh question this
operation count so this is the
operations on the left side on The
Matrix
a to finally get to
youu and anybody so which of which of
these quantities is the right B
part for that count if I add 100 squar
to 99 squar to 98 Square 97 s all the
way down 2 s and 1
squar what what what am I what have I
got
about it's one of these so tell let's
identify it first is it n certainly
not is it is it n
factorial no if it was n factorial we
would with determinance that is an
factorial put in a bad Mark against
determinance because that that uh okay
so what is
it it's and
well this is the answer it it's it's
it's this order
NQ it's like I have n
terms right I've got n terms in this sum
uh and the biggest one is n s so the the
the wor it could be would be n Cub but
it's not as bad as it's n Cub times
there's a it's
about 1/3 of n
CU that's the that's the magic uh
operation
T somehow that one3 takes account of the
fact that
the the numbers are getting smaller if
they weren't getting smaller we would
have n terms times n s would be exactly
n Cub but our numbers are getting
smaller actually do you remember where
where does 1/3 come in this I I'll even
allow a mention of
calculus so calculus can be mentioned
integration can be mentioned now in the
next minute and and not again for weeks
it's not that I don't like 1801 but 18
[Music]
okay so the answer is 1/3 and2 now I'll
just let me let me say one more thing
about
operations what about the right hand
side this was what it cost on the left
side count this is on
a but this is a that we're working with
but what's the cost on the extra column
Vector B that we're we're hanging around
here so B B it cost a lot less
obviously cuz it's just one column we
carry it through
elimination and then actually we do back
substitution let me just tell you the
answer there it's n
s so the cost for every right hand side
is
n² so let me I'll just fit that in here
for the right for the the cost of B
of B turns out to be
n²
so you see if we have as we often have
uh a matrix a and several right hand
sides uh then we pay the price on a the
higher price on a to get it split up
into L and U to do elimination on a but
then we can process every right hand
side that at low talk okay so the the
that's we really have discussed the most
fundamental algorithm of uh of for a
system of
equations
okay so uh I'm
ready to
allow row
changes I'm ready to allow now what
happen to this whole today's lecture if
there are roow
exchanges when would there be roic
exchanges they roow we need to do row
exchanges if a zero shows up in the
pivot position so I'm I'm moving then
into the final section of this
chapter which is about transposes well
we've already seen some
transposes
and uh so what's the the ti the title of
this section
is
um transposes and
permutation okay so can I say now where
does the permutation come
in let let me talk a little about
permutation so that'll be up here
permutation
so these are the matrices that I need to
do row
exchanges and I may have to do two row
exchanges is it can you invent a matrix
where I would have to do two row
exchanges and then it would come out
fine yeah let's just for the heck of
it uh so I'll put it
here uh let me do
3x3
actually why don't I just plain list all
the 3X3 permutation matrices they're a
nice little group of them what are all
the
matrices
that exchange no rows at all well I'll
include the
identity so that's a permutation Matrix
that doesn't do anything now what's the
permutation Matrix that
exchanges what is
p12 the permutation Matrix that
exchanges rows one and two would
be 0 1
0 one 0 0 right I just exchange those
rows of the identity and I've got it
okay actually I'll yeah let me let me
not clutter this
up
okay give me a complete list of all the
row exchange matrices so what are they
they're all the ways I can take the
identity Matrix and rearrange its rows
how how many will there
be how many 3x3 permutation
matrices so we keep going and get the
answer so tell me some
more zero okay what one you going to do
now
with rows one
and one and three okay one and
three leaving two
alone okay now what
else switch what do we the next easy one
is switch two and three good so I'll
leave one alone and I'll switch I'll
move number three up and number two
down okay
those are the ones that just exchange
single single a pair of
roads this guy this guy and this guy
exchang just a pair of roads but now
there are more possibilities what are
the what what's
left so tell there is another one
here what's
that it's going to move it's going to
change all roads right where should we
put them so give me a first row 0 1 0
okay now a second row say 0 0 1 and the
third guy 1 0
0 so that that is like a cycle that
puts row two moves up to row one row
three moves up to row two and Row one
moves down to row three and there's one
more which
is let's see what's left
is it 0 1
okay one 0
okay 0 1 0
okay
great six six
of six
p and and they're sort of nice because
what happens if I like
um multiply two of them
together if I multiply two of these
matrices together what can you tell me
about the
answer it's on the
list if I if I do some Ro exchanges and
I did some more row exchanges and all
together I've done row exchanges so if I
multiply
but I don't know and if I
invert then I'm just doing Ro ex changes
to get back again so so the inverses are
all there it's it's a it's a little
family of
matrices that like
uh they've got their own If I multiply
I'm still inside this group if I invert
I'm inside this group actually group is
the right name for this it's a group of
six
matrices and what about the inverses
what's the inverse of this kind for
example what's the inverse if I change
Rose one and two what's the inverse
Matrix just tell me fast the inverse of
that Matrix is if I
is if I change rows one and two then
what I should do back to get back to
where I start it is the same thing so
this thing is its own
inverse this is that's probably its own
inverse this is probably not actually I
think these are inverses of each other
oh yeah
actually the inverse is the transpose
there's a curious
fact about permutation matrixes that the
inverses are the
transposes and final moment how many are
there if I how many 4x4 permutations so
let me take
4x4 how many
ke well well
okay make a good
get 24 right 24 P okay so uh we've got
these permutation matrices and in the
next uh
lecture uh we use them so the next
lecture finishes chapter 2 and moves to
chapter
[Music]
OPP
e
for